The דף Daf is י"ד. Yud Daled. We are wrapping up the
first פרק Perek and beginning the second, and we are in the
middle of a whole series of אגדתות Aggadotas around משה's Moshe death
because יוסף Yosef buried his father, משה Moshe buried יוסף, Yosef, and
God buried משה. Moshe. We just had a beautiful little description about
him being carried by the divine wings and accompanied by the angels
during his לויה. Levayah. So we now pick up at the bottom
of י"ג עמוד ב', Yud Gimmel Amud Beis,
ויש אומרים, V'yesh Omrim, four lines from the bottom, ויש אומרים לא
מת משה. V'yesh Omrim Lo Meis Moshe. Bet you never heard that
one. We heard יעקב אבינו לא מת, Yaakov Avinu Lo Meis, that's
the famous one, but here's לא מת משה, Lo Meis Moshe, which
is interesting.
Anybody know why we say what the גמרא's Gemara basis for יעקב
אבינו לא מת? Yaakov Avinu Lo Meis? It doesn't say ומת. Vamas.
It doesn't say,
right, it doesn't say that he died. It says exactly.
It says ויאסף אל עמיו Vayeiosef el amav but it never says
that he was
מת. Meis. Okay, by משה Moshe it says he died. So how
are we going to say משה Moshe didn't die? כתיב הכא וימת
שם, Kesiv hacha vayamas sham, okay, וכתיב התם ויהי שם עם השם.
Ukesiv hasam vayehi sham im Hashem. מה
להלן עומד ומשמש, Mah halon omed umishamesh, when he was there with
God he was there attending like he was, you know, he was
there attending to God, אף כאן עומד ומשמש, Af kan omed umishamesh,
he didn't really die. Which of course you know you understand the
comparison that's being made, which is, you know, if משה Moshe was
basically at such a high spiritual level, how was he anyway at
הר סיני Har Sinai for forty days and forty nights without eating
and drinking? He obviously was existing in some type of a spiritual
and non-physical sense, you know, non-normally physical sense. So maybe what happened
to his body during that time? Maybe he had become all disembodied
spirit during that time with God. And maybe that's also what happened
שם Sham to הכא, Hacha, you know, maybe the death is just
an apparent death because ultimately his body is lying there but he's
there with God, his spirit is there with God, and he ultimately
is not really dead. So it's an interesting comparison.
Aren't all spirits with God?
No, but I mean like he hasn't completely departed his spirit. He's
only there because he's connecting to God like what happened during the
forty days when he was at הר סיני. Har Sinai. מנהג המקום.
Minhag Hamakom. What?
מנהג המקום.
Minhag
Hamakom.
This statement, the statement comes right after
the לויה Levayah and the הספד. He-sped. Exactly. This is a different
approach.
Where was he buried?
This is a
different approach, he didn't die.
Okay, yes, he just didn't need any sustenance for those forty days
he was there, he shut down.
Right. I understand, but I'm trying to explain how the גמרא Gemara
can imagine since it says וימת Vayamas without him saying he died.
And I'm trying to see it rather than just making a גזירה
שוה, Gezeirah Shavah, maybe it's trying to say well let's consider what
really was going on there for the forty days and maybe something
similar is going on here and it only was an apparent type
of a death but not an actual death. It is interesting, you
know, again,
because probably the whole challenge sort of of the death of משה
Moshe is here he is,
you know, the most powerful figure, the lawgiver of Israel, the one
from whom
all the תורה Torah comes. So how do you deal, on the
one hand you could say that's exactly why he couldn't go into
the land, like we had to be able to transition after him,
you know, exist without him. But nevertheless once the תורה Torah starts
with ולא ידע איש את קבורתו Velo yada ish es kevuraso and
sort of it's all wrapped up in mystery and who buries him,
the only one there was God to bury him, so the fact
that there can develop an idea that well maybe he didn't even
really die, we want to hold on to that idea, you can
understand.
So the גמרא Gemara now continues, ויקבור אותו בגי בארץ מואב מול
בית פעור, Vayikbor oso bagai be'eretz Moav mul Beis Peor, and he,
presumably God, buried him in the valley in the land of מואב
Moav opposite בית פעור. Beis Peor. So there's a lot of identifiers
here. There are three identifiers: in the valley, in the land of
מואב, Moav, opposite בית פעור. Beis Peor. אמר ברכיה סימן בתוך סימן,
Amar Brachyah siman b'soch siman,
there's one identifier in the middle of another, like in the valley,
in ארץ מואב, Eretz Moav, you know, it's like multiple identifiers. ואפילו
הכי ולא ידע איש את קבורתו. Va'afilu hachi velo yada ish es
kevuraso. But even so, even though the תורה Torah gave all these
identifiers, it was still unable to know where he was buried. Again,
sort of like it's wrapped in mystery and we're going to see
something
miraculous prevent his grave from ever being discovered even with all these
identifiers. שכך שלחו מלכות הרשעה, She-kach shalchu Malchus Harishah, the evil kingdom,
meaning Rome, sent אצל גיסטרא של בית פעור Eizel Gistra shel Beis
Peor
to the leader of בית פעור, Beis Peor, גיסטרא Gistra apparently means
leader. הראנו היכן משה קבור, Hareinu heicha Moshe kavor,
show us where משה Moshe is buried. Sort of like the search
for the Lost Ark, not the Raiders of the Lost Ark when
they go searching for Noah's Ark on Mount Ararat. So go, if
we've got this mountain let's go search it, tell us where משה
Moshe is buried. עמדו למעלה נדמה
להם למטה. Amdu l'ma'alah nidmeh lahem l'matah. So then when they were
at a high elevation, I mean it was in a valley, but
anyway when they were at high elevation it seemed that the place
where they had seen like it looked like his grave site, whatever
they were looking for, it seemed that it was below them. למטה
נדמה להם למעלה. L'matah nidmeh lahem l'ma'alah. When they then went down,
it looked like it was above them where the place they were
looking for. So נחלקו לשתי כיתות, Necheleku l'shtei kitos, so they divided
up into two groups, cover their bases. So אותן שעומדים למעלה otan
she'omdim lemala the ones that were higher on higher elevation, נדמה להם
למטה nidmeh lahem lemata it seemed like the grave was lower. למטה
lemata those who were at the lower place, נדמה להם למעלה nidmeh
lahem lemala it seemed like the grave was higher. Okay, so basically
there's obviously some magic that is not magic wrong word anyway, but
some miracle that is protecting it to ensure that it can never
be even though you've it's been identified you'll never find it. Okay,
לקיים מה שנאמר lekayem ma shene'emar
and obviously the point there is exactly the same point of transitioning
beyond. It's that if you know Moshe's grave site then it becomes
a place of worship, right then he becomes deified. So the whole
point is you've got to move into the land of Canaan without
Moshe, without knowing his grave site, you know, he was the like
you know the Torah ends, you know, לא קם נביא עוד בישראל
lo kam navi od beyisrael like דווקא davka because he was the
greatest person and the greatest נביא navi we have to be able
to live our lives without him. So therefore it's impossible to find
his grave. לקיים מה שנאמר ולא ידע איש את קבורתו. lekayem ma
shene'emar velo yada ish et kevurato. רבי חמא ברבי חנינא אמר Rabbi
Chama b'Rabbi Chanina amar אף משה רבנו אינו יודע היכן קבור. af
Moshe Rabbeinu eino yodea heichan kavur. Even Moshe didn't know where he
was buried. כתיב הכא ksiv hacha ולא ידע איש את קבורתו velo
yada ish et kevurato he was dead at the time but I
guess okay he told him where to
go so to speak. What does that mean?
I don't know.
Maybe it means his spirit doesn't know. ולא ידע איש את קבורתו
velo yada ish et kevurato וכתיב התם uchsiv hatam וזאת הברכה אשר
בירך משה איש האלוהים vezot haberacha asher berach Moshe ish ha'elokim so
ולא ידע איש velo yada ish who else is the איש ish
if not Moshe? Okay. ואמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא ve'amar Rabbi Chama
b'Rabbi Chanina מפני מה נקבר משה אצל בית פעור? mipnei ma nikbar
Moshe etzel Beit Peor? Why was he buried by בית פעור? Beit
Peor? כדי לכפר על מעשה פעור kedai lechaper al ma'aseh Peor to
atone for the sin of פעור Peor right because of the sin
of בנות מואב benot moav which is in that location. ואמר רבי
חמא ברבי חנינא ve'amar Rabbi Chama b'Rabbi Chanina מאי דכתיב mai d'ichtiv
what's meant אחרי ה' אלוהיכם תלכו acharei Hashem Elokeichem telechu you should
follow after Hashem your God? וכי אפשר לו לאדם לילך אחר שכינה?
vechi efshar lo leadam leilech achar shechina? Is it possible for a
person to walk after God? והלא כבר נאמר כי ה' אלוהיך אש
אוכלה הוא vahalo kevar ne'emar ki Hashem Elokecha esh ochla hu God
is a consuming fire? How do we how do we say like
be close to God, walk after God and so on? The only
reason we're quoting this by the way is it's the same רבי
חמא ברבי חנינא, Rabbi Chama b'Rabbi Chanina, doesn't directly attach. אלא ela
but to teach you לילך אחר מידותיו leilech achar midotav to follow
after His ways של הקדוש ברוך הוא. shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. מה
הוא מלביש ערומים ma hu malbish arumim דכתיב d'ichtiv ויעש ה' אלוהים
לאדם ולאשתו כותנות עור וילבישם vaya'as Hashem Elokim leadam uleishto kotnot or
vayalbishem
the same way God clothed the naked as it says that He
made for Adam and his wife garments of leather and He cloaked
them, He cloaked them, אף אתה הלבש ערומים af ata halbesh arumim
you should also clothe the naked. הקדוש ברוך הוא ביקר חולים Hakadosh
Baruch Hu bikker cholim God visits the sick דכתיב d'ichtiv וירא אליו
ה' באלוני ממרא vayeira elav Hashem be'alonei mamre
God appeared to Avraham in the terebinths of Mamre after he had
done the ברית מילה brit milah so apparently that's a ביקור חולים,
bikur cholim, אף אתה ביקר חולים af ata bikker cholim even you
should visit the sick. הקדוש ברוך הוא ניחם אבלים Hakadosh Baruch Hu
nicham avelim God consoled the mourners דכתיב d'ichtiv ויהי אחרי מות אברהם
ויברך אלוהים את יצחק בנו vayehi acharei mot Avraham vayevarech Elokim et
Yitzchak beno and presumably that blessing is that He visited him after
the death in order to console, אף אתה נחם
אבלים af ata nachem avelim virtue you should also console the mourners.
הקדוש ברוך הוא קבר מתים Hakadosh Baruch Hu kavar metim God buried
the dead דכתיב d'ichtiv ויקבור אותו בגי vayikbor oto bagai so that
does tie back, אף אתה קבור מתים af ata kevor metim
you should also bury the dead. So I want to say one
or two things about this beautiful דרשה. drasha. Number one is that
it's also it's very interesting to hold this up against another classic
דרשה drasha that speaks about going after God or being like God,
you know, והלכת בדרכיו vehalachta bidrachav which it says maybe פרק חמישי
perek chamishi no, that's another one but I'm not going to talk
about that one. But this is מה הוא רחום אף אתה רחום
מה הוא חנון אף אתה חנון. ma hu rachum af ata rachum
ma hu chanun af ata chanun. And that really speaks about like
two different approaches towards ethics. One is exactly, one focuses on character
traits and the other focuses on actions,
a very different type of an approach, you know, actions focuses on
ultimately what good are we doing in the world. It doesn't really
matter, you know, whether it's your inclination or not your inclination, maybe
in some ways it's even like Kant said that if I don't
want to be nice to people and I don't want to give
charity and I force myself to give charity it's better because it
shows that I'm doing it out of a sense of obligation and
I'm prepared to do it even if it's not my nature. And
ultimately that says an ethical deed is one that actually does good
and it doesn't matter about your, you know, your personality. Another approach
says no, the whole point of ethics is to perfect the character.
So for example you have an extreme example about this in Rambam
where Rambam says that the reason, you know, the famous line in
פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot which says הכול לפי רוב המעשה ולא לפי
גודל
המעשה. hakol lefi rov hama'aseh velo lefi godel hama'aseh. It's all based
on the the the the amount of the deed and not the
size of the deed. Like what, what does that mean? So Rambam
says what it means is that exactly, better to give one dollar
of צדקה tzedakah a hundred times than to give a hundred dollars
of צדקה tzedakah at once. Because if you give one dollar's צדקה
tzedakah a hundred times you would have cultivated in yourself more of
the character of, you know, of of empathy and of giving צדקה
tzedakah and of right and of you know and and of giving
charity and so on and you do more to cultivate your character.
And there's a lot of things in Rambam's פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayot
on פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot where he has a consistent approach that
he pretty much reads like everything there about perfecting your character. Even
things like giving money to the poor, the purpose of it is
to perfect your character.
So it's not
just a list of action, no, it's no ethical.
No, you need the action to develop your character, but the goal
is the perfection of character as opposed to the goal is to
help people and make a better world. That's really the difference. If
you read the רמב"ם, Rambam, trust me on this, you can do
it and then we can talk. Read the רמב"ם Rambam consistently in
פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayos in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, pretty much every
ethical deed there is described because he opens with the שמונה פרקים
Shemonah Perakim which is about perfection of character and every ethical deed
there is described as a means towards perfecting your character, not an
end in good in itself. I mean, that's an extreme formulation of
it. Similarly for example רמב"ם Rambam says that גמרא Gemara says that
a person shouldn't say, you know, well whatever,
long story, like I don't want to do the sin I want
to but God makes me, you should only say that by the
ritual actions but by ethical actions the point is that you should
want to do it and you should make that part of your
character. So the point getting back to this is that this is
an important one that isn't quoted as much which emphasizes the idea
of being like God as focusing on actions, not focusing on, you
know, character traits, not
רחום וחנון Rachum V'chanun etc., doesn't matter what you are, matters what
you do. Exactly. To be מה תשדי Ma Tishadei is defined by
actions not by character traits. Yes, Gemma.
I just wonder if that statement can be related back to our
larger context of סוטה, Sotah, like especially because we started the פרק
Perek with like oh well you know like men marry the people
they
deserve, so maybe you know maybe he had it coming or maybe
there was something going on in marriage and this is like kind
of coming at the end of the סוגיא Sugya of like okay
but at the end of the day it matters what you do.
Oh that's a very nice point, right, very nice. So whatever sort
of character you are ultimately you decide on the actions that you're
doing. Yes.
Because God is perfect so he doesn't have to need any development
of his character.
Right.
Exactly. Exactly. But the רחום וחנון Rachum V'chanun says exactly God is
already perfect in character and we have to emulate that character. Right.
So which one are we focusing on? The other important point to
make is another one of the other important points is you know
I also thought that maybe it's coming here juxtaposed to the story
of משה Moshe because again it's
like משה, Moshe, like you want to like you know there's this
inclination like you have to hide משה's Moshe burial place because you'd
want to like worship him and deify him and so on. You
know but the point is ultimately like just figure out how to
be like him. You know that's the way in which the same
way here like by God the goal is to act like it's
not to try to like you know you can never really you
can't be God you can't be משה Moshe but try to figure
out how to do how to act in a similar way. Maybe
that's a little bit of the juxtaposition. The other point I wanted
to say about it is the fact that it concretizes specific actions
is very important. You know רמב"ם Rambam says all of these things,
ביקור חולים, Bikkur Cholim, ניחום אבלים, Nichum Aveilim, what do we have,
הכנסת אורחים, Hachnasas Orchim, did they have הכנסת אורחים, Hachnasas Orchim, הלבשת
ערומים, Halbashas Arumim, you know all of these types of things are
under the rubric of ואהבת לרעך כמוך. V'ahavta L'reiacha Kamocha. But if
you just left them under ואהבת לרעך כמוך V'ahavta L'reiacha Kamocha nobody
would do them. But because חז"ל Chazal speak very concretely about an
obligation called ניחום אבלים Nichum Aveilim and an obligation called ביקור חולים
Bikkur Cholim and an obligation called הכנסת אורחים, Hachnasas Orchim,
right, it very much concretizes it and it really becomes then you
know something that you can really identify with that particular action. So
there's a real power and in a way that's much more concrete
than oh you should be חנון Chanun you should be רחום. Rachum.
Right. When you concretize it of concrete action it's also something that's
much easier to emulate. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues and
the following. Now that we mentioned the פסוק Pasuk of כתנות עור,
Kasnos Or, let's talk about that. So we have some things we
want to say about that. Okay so כתנות עור, Kasnos Or, רב
ושמואל, Rav U'Shmuel, חד אמר דבר הבא מן העור, Chad amar davar
haba min ha-or, something that comes from leather. Okay. וחד אמר דבר
שהעור נהנה ממנו. V'chad amar davar sheha-or ne'neh mimenu. No, it means
it means garments for the skin for for you know that that
the skin benefits from. So רש"י Rashi says it means sort of
like linen garments I guess things that feel soft and nice against
the skin. דרש רבי שמלאי, Darash Rabi Simlai, תורה תחלתה גמילות חסדים
וסופה גמילות חסדים. Torah techilasa gemilus chasadim v'sofah gemilus chasadim. Right
in the beginning it's acts of גמילות חסדים Gemilus Chasadim and in
the end it's acts of גמילות חסדים. Gemilus Chasadim. Again focusing on
the type of of of actions that we are that are being
modeled for us. תחלתה גמילות חסדים Techilasa gemilus chasadim דכתיב ויעש ה'
אלהים לאדם ולאשתו כתנות עור וילבישם, D'ksiv Vayayas Hashem Elokim l'adam u'l'ishto
kasnos or vayalbisha'im, וסופה גמילות חסדים V'sofah gemilus chasadim דכתיב ויקבור אותו
בגיא. D'ksiv Vayikbor oso bagai.
So basically he's picking up on two of the things that were
said in the previous דרשה, Drasha, but rather than saying you know
you should be like God and A B C and D, it's
focusing on the character of the תורה, Torah, that the תורה Torah
opens with an act of גמילות חסדים Gemilus Chasadim and ends with
an act of גמילות חסדים Gemilus Chasadim to tell you something about
like a predominant like theme about you know what the תורה Torah
is about. Right? There's a lot of things going on in the
תורה, Torah, a lot of מצוות, Mitzvos, a lot of stories, like
it opens and closes with גמילות חסדים. Gemilus Chasadim. That should tell
you something. Okay so ויקבור אותו בגיא. Vayikbor oso bagai. דרש רבי
שמלאי, Darash Rabi Simlai, מפני מה נתאוה משה רבינו Mipnei mah nisaveh
Moshe Rabbeinu
now back to משה. Moshe. Why did משה Moshe desire להכנס לארץ
ישראל L'hikanes l'Eretz Yisrael to go into the land of ישראל? Israel?
וכי לאכול מפריה הוא צריך, Kichei l'echol mi-piryah hu tzarich,
what did he want to like eat like a Jaffa orange, like
what was the big deal? או לשבוע מטובה הוא צריך, O l'isboa
mi-tuvah hu tzarich,
or just in any ways benefit from like oh to a nice
land I'll sit under you know the eucalyptus tree or something. No,
what was it about? No, אלא כך אמר משה. Ella kach amar
Moshe.
This is what משה Moshe said. הרבה מצוות נצטוו Harbeh mitzvos nitzvu
Israel
has been commanded many מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvot*, ואין מתקיימים אלא בארץ ישראל
*v’ein mitkaymim ella b’Eretz Yisrael*, and they’re only fulfilled in the land
of Israel. אכנס אני לארץ *ekanes ani la'aretz* כדי שיתקיימו כולן על
ידי *kedei sheyitkaymu kulan al yadi*, let me go into the land
that they should all be fulfilled by me and I’ll be able
to do all the מצוות mitzvos. *mitzvot*. So אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך
הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu *amar leih HaKadosh Baruch Hu*, God said to
him, כלום אתה מבקש אלא לקבל שכר schar *kelum atah mevakesh ella
lekabel sachar*? What, you want, you only want to do it because
you want to get credit for it? מעלה אני עליך כאילו עשיתם
*ma'aleh ani alecha ke'ilu asitam*,
I’ll give you credit like you did them.
שנאמר *she’ne'emar*, alright, alright, לכן אחלק לו ברבים *lachen achalek lo varabbim*,
I will divide his portion in the masses, ואת עצומים יחלק שלל
*ve’et atzumim yachalek shalal* and with the mighty he will divide the
booty. תחת אשר הערה למות נפשו *tachat asher he'erah lamavet nafsho*, because
he has exposed his soul to death. ואת פושעים נמנה *ve’et poshim
nimnah*, and with the sinners he was counted, we’ll see what that
means, והוא חטא רבים נשא *vehu chet rabbim nasa*, and he the
sin of the masses carried, ולפושעים יפגיע *velafoshim yapgia*,
and for the sinners he will entreat. לכן אחלק לו ברבים *lachen
achalek lo varabbim*, now we’re going to explain each part of that
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*. לכן אחלק לו ברבים *lachen achalek lo varabbim*, therefore
I will divide from the masses, יכול כאחרונים ולא כראשונים *yachol ke'achronim
velo kerishonim*, maybe like later great people but not like the early
great people, maybe his portion will only be like the laters, not
like the great early ones. תלמוד לומר ואת עצומים יחלק שלל *talmud
lomar ve’et atzumim yachalek shalal*, with the mighty ones he will divide
the booty, כאברהם יצחק ויעקב שהן עצומים בתורה ובמצוות *ke’Avraham Yitzchak ve’Yaakov
shehen atzumim baTorah u’vemitzvot*, like Avraham, Yitzchak, and Yaakov who were so
mighty in terms of Torah and mitzvot. תחת אשר הערה למות נפשו
*tachat asher he'erah lamavet nafsho*, now back to that part of the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, because he exposed his soul to die, himself to
die, שמסר עצמו למיתה *she’masar atzmo lemitah*,
he was prepared to die. שנאמר *she’ne'emar*, ואם אין מחני נא מספרך
*ve’im ayin mecheni na misifrecha*, and if you don’t do that, you
know, you don’t forgive them, you might as well wipe me from
your book, which presumably he meant like just kill me now, which
is not necessarily, I don’t know if that’s פשט *pshat*, but anyway.
ואת פושעים נמנה *ve’et poshim nimnah*, and with sinners he was counted,
let’s see what that means, שנמנה עם מתי מדבר *she’nimnah im metei
midbar*, that he was counted with, he was among those who died
in the desert, like he ultimately, you know, now again why is
that like a positive thing? But I guess it’s sort of like
the captain going down with the ship, you know, or maybe he
to some degree took some responsibility for the fact that they did
not, you know, live up to the test and ultimately, you know,
they had to die in the wilderness. So it’s interesting there what
exactly the positive thing there is, maybe just, you know, because he
suffered and he died in the desert and didn’t go into the
land. והוא חטא רבים נשא *vehu chet rabbim nasa*, he carried the
sin of the masses, שכיפר על מעשה העגל *she’kiper al ma’aseh ha’egel*,
he atoned for the sin of the calf, ולפושעים יפגיע *velafoshim yapgia*,
and for the sinners he would, he entreated, שביקש רחמים על פושעי
ישראל שיחזרו בתשובה *she’bikesh rachamim al poshei Yisrael she’yachzeru bitshuvah*, he asked
for God’s mercy that the sinners should repent, ואין פגיעה אלא תפילה
*ve’ein pegiah ella tefillah*, and פגיעה *pegiah* means entreat, שנאמר *she’ne'emar*, ואתה
אל תתפלל בעד העם הזה ואל תשא בעדם רנה ותפילה *ve’atah al
titpalel be’ad ha'am hazeh ve’al tisa ba’adam rinah u’tefillah*, do not pray
for this people, ואל תפגע בי *ve’al tifga bi*, and do not
entreat me. So משה Moshe *Moshe* there, although he could not enter
the land, was given this full credit as if he had entered
into the land. Now Michael had a question. I also have a
question, but we’ll start with Michael’s question.
So Michael’s question sounds like, oh, כלום אתה מבקש אלא לקבל שכר
*kelum atah mevakesh ella lekabel sachar*? Or it sounds so mercenary.
And what about אל תהיו כעבדים המשמשים את הרב על מנת לקבל
פרס *al tihyu ke'avadim hameshamshim et harav al menat lekabel peras*? Right.
So one question is, what does it mean that he’s, I’m just
pulling something up, what does it mean that he’s doing it, who
said משה *Moshe* was only doing it לקבל שכר *lekabel sachar*? Like
there’s a famous story of the וילנא גאון *Vilna Gaon* that the
וילנא גאון *Vilna Gaon* saw somebody on סוכות *Sukkot* that had the
most beautiful מהודר אתרוג *mehudar etrog*. So he said to the person,
he said, could you lend me your אתרוג *etrog* so I can
do it to be יוצא *yotzei* the מצוה *mitzvah*, I’ll be able
to do the מצוה *mitzvah* with such a beautiful אתרוג *etrog*? And
the person said, I’ll only let you use my אתרוג *etrog* if
I get all of your שכר *sachar* for the מצוה *mitzvah*. So
the וילנא גאון *Vilna Gaon* agreed. So he took the אתרוג *etrog*
and like the students saw him and they said like he had
never been happier to do such a מצוה *mitzvah* in his life.
And they said, רבי *Rebbe*, why are you so happy? He said,
because every other time I couldn’t know if ultimately maybe there was
some reason I was doing it because of the שכר *sachar*. Now
I know I’m doing it just to serve הקדוש ברוך הוא *HaKadosh
Baruch Hu* because I’m not getting any שכר *sachar* for this, it’s
just לשם המצוה *leshem hamitzvah*. So, you know, I mean, exactly, what
does it mean you’re doing it to get the שכר *sachar*? So
that’s question number one. You know, question number two I would say
is, if somebody would ask you, look, you know, there’s a,
you know, some more, you know, חרדי *Charedi* now, I think the
חרדי *Charedi* more like more okay with the idea of the מדינה
*medinah* or they, whatever, than they used to be. I don't know
how much they embrace it as a religious thing. But anyway, but
certainly, you know, there was many, you know, definitely, you know, for
many חרדים *Charedim*, it’s important to go to Israel to do the
מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot*, right? Because you get more מצוות mitzvos, התלויות בארץ
*mitzvot hateluyot ba'aretz* if you’re going to Israel. But there’s no concept
of being in the land as part of a, you know, maybe
there is now. Certainly there hadn't been in the past, you know,
as part of some like larger, even not messianic, like larger national
identity, you know, in a sense of a mission and, you know,
God put us on here to be a people in the land
and so go to the land in order to get the extra
מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot*, you know, there’s a lot of מצוות mitzvos. *mitzvot*
you can do in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael? *Eretz Yisrael* that you
can’t do elsewhere. You know, so it’s funny that this gets reduced
to the מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvot*. Oh, you had a couple of מצוות
mitzvos, *mitzvot* you needed to do. Like you haven’t done all the
מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot*, you wanted to go into the
land. That’s why? The whole point of going into the land wasn’t
it that to be with the people when they finally came into
the land, that it would allow them to actualize their whole self
as a nation, you know, under God, you know, as a nation
defined by the תורה Torah. *Torah*, to build the nation, to have
to actualize... That's like the whole vision. Is that really what it
is? Is it just to get the מצוות? mitzvos. So I think
that it's interesting to compare
this, if I'm not forgetting, to a statement of רב שמלאי Rav
Simlai that ends מסכת... this is רב שמלאי Rav Simlai who says
this, right? Statement of רב שמלאי Rav Simlai that ends מסכת מכות.
Masechet Makkos. Let me just see quickly if I can find it.
Hold on.
I think רב שמלאי Rav Simlai was the one that gave the
number of 613.
I think you're correct about
that. There's a number of those traditions, he's one of them.
I'm pretty sure he's the one that gave the number 613. Hold
on. Rather than going straight to גמרא מכות, Gemara Makkos, I can
just type it into Google because Google knows everything.
Let's take a quick look.
It is pretty funny how, oops, I wrote שמחה, Simcha, but let's
see. Anyway, how it becomes the repository because everything that anybody knows
is out there on whatever. Okay. So, this association between משה and
the מצוות, mitzvos is that because אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham, Yitzchak, v'Yaakov
were מקיים מצוות mekayeim mitzvos outside of ארץ ישראל?
Eretz Yisrael, No. I don't think so. Just they are the, I
don't think it's connected. But it's connected to not going into ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael that's what I...
No, no, no. You get the reward, you get the reward as
the greatest people. I don't think it's directly connected.
Anyway, so it says, right, דרש רב שמלאי שש
מאות ושלש עשרה מצוות נאמרו לו למשה מסיני
darash Rav
Simlai sheish
meios u'shlosh esrei mitzvos ne'emru lo l'Moshe mi'Sinai etc. etc. אמר רב
המנונא מאי קרא תורה צוה לנו משה amar Rav Hamnuna mai kra
Torah tziva lanu Moshe etc. מכות כ"ג עמוד ב'. Makkos chaf gimmel
amud beis. I was right! I think I was right. Anyway, hold
on. So the reason I'm also looking for it is because I
think it also ties... oh, it's כ"ג עמוד ב' chaf gimmel amud
beis although כ"ד עמוד ב'. chaf daled amud beis. The reason I'm
looking for it is because I think it also ties into... yes,
I was right. Look at this. אמר רבי חנינא בן עקשיא אומר
רצה הקדוש ברוך הוא לזכות את ישראל לפיכך הרבה להם תורה ומצוות
שנאמר ה' חפץ למען צדקו יגדיל תורה ויאדיר. amar Rabi Chanina ben
Akashya omer ratza Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'zakos es Yisrael l'fichach hirbah lahem
Torah u'mitzvos shene'emar Hashem chafetz l'ma'an tzidko yagdil Torah v'yadir. Does that
sound familiar? Okay, so that's in a משנה. Mishnah. And then on
that, רב שמלאי Rav Simlai says 613 מצוות. mitzvos, So in a
way, the 613 מצוות mitzvos. is an elaboration of the statement of
הקדוש ברוך הוא הרבה להם תורה ומצוות, hirbah lahem Torah u'mitzvos, לזכות
את ישראל. l'zakos es Yisrael. So it's exactly the same idea of
look at the number of מצוות, mitzvos and the more מצוות mitzvos
you do, the more שכר you do. It's all about the quantity
of מצוות. mitzvos It's a very similar type of a focus on
just x number of מצוות, mitzvos getting more מצוות, mitzvos 613 לזכות
ישראל. l'zakos Yisrael. Now, some scholars, by the way, have suggested that
that point of הרבה הקדוש ברוך הוא תורה ומצוות כדי לזכות את
ישראל hirbah Hakadosh Baruch Hu Torah u'mitzvos k'dei l'zakos es Yisrael is
a response to Christianity where the Christian approach is that God gave
us the law in order that we could, in order that because
we're so that we should sin. How do you exactly articulate it?
It's the מצוות are basically a way of leading... nobody knows what
I'm talking about? Yeah, or you're saying that to show that you
need to be dependent on Jesus because in no way can you
do all the מצוות. Yeah, but ultimately, and ultimately that the law
is, a matter of spirit and just reaching out. Exactly. But there's
something more about that, that ultimately having all of the מצוות reflects
a lowly state, a non-spirit state, and so on. And this is
a direct response and that says, no, the ריבוי מצוות ribbu'i mitzvos
is לזכות ישראל. l'zakos Yisrael. It's exactly what gives us, allows us
to reach a very high spiritual state, and only the law is
the way through towards redemption and merit. Anyway, whatever it is, it's
a focus on the number of מצוות, and that very much fits
in here with this focus, which is, if you think about it,
very strange. It reduces the whole point of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael.
to the issue of the number of מצוות. Do you think we
should view him in this particular context? What? Yeah, I mean, I
think that he's part of this connection of תרי"ג מצוות Taryag mitzvos
and לזכות את ישראל. l'zakos es Yisrael. And there could be part
of a, I don't think that we can infer from here that
that's the only value he gives to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael, I
think he could be using this to support a particular approach, a
framework, an emphasis about the importance of the number of מצוות and
as many מצוות as you do, it's all a good thing and
you should try to do as many מצוות as possible and so
on. Obviously we always try to do as many מצוות as possible,
very much concretely. Like, here, there's a list and so on. When
did רב שמלאי live?
I'm not sure. I mean, I know that there's been work on
that.
He's post-חורבן, post-Churban, very much a post-חורבן post-Churban perspective. Yeah, in other
words, it's the even if there's more מצוות you can do in
ארץ ישראל, where the really the core of one's ideational identity is
קיום מצוות kiyum mitzvos wherever
you live.
Hence משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu himself didn't need to actually go into
the land. Yeah, but the point you're saying, because משה רבינו Moshe
Rabbeinu wanted to, so you're saying God is saying, don't worry about
it. Just you're saying we shouldn't worry so much that the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash was נחרב. nechrav.
I'm sorry, one more time? What were you saying?
No, in other words, God is telling משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* that
actually he doesn't have to enter ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. In other
words, his leadership and Jewish identity is not dependent upon being in
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. It's not, it's not placed there.
Right. Oh, well that could be also. Okay. So anyway, finally, that's
what you're saying. Yeah.
Here,
so yes, the Christian belief is as that the law is in
the... the law, no, not only that, the law reflects bondage. One
covenant is from Mount Sinai and bears children who are slaves. This
is הגר *Hagar*, etc. etc. So anyway, you know, the law represents
a bondage people, a non-free people, a non-redeemed people and so on.
Okay, moving on. Okay. המקנא לאשתו *Hamekaneh leishto*. Okay,
and also interesting to go back to Jenna's point about the difference
about like character and then how do you actually act on it
and what are the deeds that you do. Let's take a look
now at the second פרק *perek*. היה מביא את מנחתה בתוך כפיפה
מצרית *Haya mevi es minchasah besoch kefifah mitzris*. Now we get to
the everything...
did we finish the first פרק *perek*?
Yeah, yep, yep. היה מביא את מנחתה בתוך כפיפה מצרית *Haya mevi
es minchasah besoch kefifah mitzris*, they would bring her, he, the husband,
because actually if you look at the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* it is
the husband that is bringing her to the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash.
*Beis Hamikdash* and bringing her מנחה mincha *mincha*, he is sort of
the actor here. He would bring her מנחה mincha. *mincha* in a
type of an Egyptian
basket, some type of a vessel, you know, basically meaning like of
a... of a...
made out of some non-fine material, you know, some... ונותן על ידיה
*venosan al yadeha* and would put it on her hands כדי לייגעה
*kedei leyaga'ah* in order to weary her. כל המנחות kol haminchot. תחילתן
וסופן בכלי שרת bechli sharet, *Kol menachos techilasam vesofam bicheli shares*, all
מנחות menachot *minchos* would start and end with a כלי שרת kli
sharet, *keli shares*, וזו תחילתה בכפיפה מצרית *vezo techilasah bekefifah mitzris*, and
this begins not with a holy vessel, a כלי שרת kli sharet.
*keli shares*, but with this mundane and lowly vessel. וסופה בכלי שרת
bechli sharet. *vesofah bichli shares*, but in the end it's put in
a כלי שרת kli sharet. *keli shares* because obviously you have to
offer it as a מנחה mincha *mincha*. כל המנחות טעונות שמן ולבונה
*Kol hamenachos teunos shemen ulevonah*, all the מנחות menachot *minchos* demand oil
and frankincense. וזו אינה טעונה לא שמן ולא לבונה levonah *Vezo einah
teunah lo shemen velo levonah*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
ask that מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei* also does not have שמן ולבונה
*shemen ulevonah*, but okay. We will see about that. For certain... it
is you know, various like times when like there's a קרבן korban,
עולה ויורד *korban oleh veyored*, various times when for sins, you know,
normal sin you can't bring a מנחה mincha *mincha* but some sins
you're allowed to bring a מנחה mincha *mincha*. You know when it's
like one of these things that bases on how much wealth you
have. Exactly. כל המנחות באות מן החיטין *Kol menachos ba'os min hachittin*,
all מנחות menachot *minchos*
came from wheat, זו באה מן השעורין *zo ba'ah min hase'orin*, and
this came from barley. Now there's one other מנחה mincha *mincha* that
comes from barley. Again, barley is a very animal type of food,
right? It's not, yeah, it's cheaper, but it's, yeah, it's lowly. מנחת
העומר אף על פי שבאה מן השעורין *Minchas ha'omer af al pi
sheba'ah min hase'orin*,
now it is true that the עומר *Omer* would come from barley,
but היא הייתה באה גרש *hi hayah ba'ah geres*, that would come
גרש *geres* וזו באה קמח *vezo ba'ah kemach*. So what's the difference?
So גרש *geres* רש״י *Rashi* says is the... is what corresponds by
barley to the idea of סולת *soles* by wheat, which means fine
flour. So גרש *geres* might be barley but it's very sifted and
refined flour. That's how רש״י *Rashi* is doing it.
I know it says גרש ירחים *geresh yeruchim*. Isn't it גרש *geresh*?
גרש כרמל *Geresh Carmel* or גרש *geres*? גרש *geresh* כרמל *Carmel*. גרש
*geresh*. I'm sorry, you're right, גרש *geresh*, גרש *geresh*. You're right, my
mistake. Okay, so גרש *geresh*. Okay, so גרש *geresh* is refined, very
refined barley, which flour, which made it at least you know fit
to be eaten. But this is coming... this is a type of
a bran. רבן גמליאל אומר כשם שמעשיה מעשה בהמה behemah, כך קרבנה
מאכל בהמה *Rabban Gamliel omer kesheim shema'aseha ma'aseh behemah kach korbanah ma'achal
behemah*. The same way her actions, you know, until now we've just
been saying that it's lowly, it's not refined, but he connects the
dots. The same way she acted like an animal, her... her... her
sacrifice is the food of an animal. Now again, this labeling her
she acted like an animal again we're continuing this idea that this
presumption of her guilt, right? You know, because how do you know,
maybe she's totally innocent? There's all this presumption. כדי לייגעה *kedei leyaga'ah*,
we're going to weary her. Why are we going to weary her?
Because we want her to admit, we're assuming she's guilty, we want
her to admit, right? When we had the whole sort of story
before, right, you know, and it said the whole מידה כנגד מידה
*middah keneged middah*, all of it is reinforcing and this reinforces the
מידה כנגד מידה *middah keneged middah*, again, that presumption of guilt. It
is worth taking a quick look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*. תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* says the following. מביא את מנחתה *Mevi es minchasah*, אין סדר
המשנה כסדר הפרשה מכוונים *ein seder hamishnah keseder haparshah mechuvonim*, says תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos*. Actually, the order given in the המשנה *Mishnah* is not
the same as the order in the Torah. שהרי כך סדר הפרשה
*Sheharei kach seder haparshah*, here's what you have in the פרשה parashah
*parshah*. קינוי וסתירה *Kinuy uvestirah*, okay, that's how our מסכת *maseches* began.
מעלה אישה ומביא את מנחתה *Ma'aleh isha umevi es minchasah*, right? Remember
in the previous פרק *perek* we already talked about the whole ritual
about rending her garments and doing all of that, and now we're
talking about the מנחה mincha *mincha*. In the Torah, you first bring
the מנחה mincha *mincha*, okay, ומביא מנחתה *umevi minchasah*, הכהן מביא כלי
חרס ונותן לתוכו חצי לוג מים מן הכיור ונותן בו עפר *hacohen
mevi svali cheres venosein letocho chatzi log mayim min hakiyor venosein bo
afar*. So then you go get the water ready. מעמיד את האישה
בשער ניקנור ואוחז בבגדיה וסותר את שערה *ma'amid es ha'ishah besha'ar nikanor
ve'ochez begadeha vesoser es se'arah*. So after the מנחה mincha. *mincha* and
after the water is ready, the husband's scraped in too yet, but
it's ready, okay, then you dishevel her and you, you know, you
do this rending of her garments. ונותן מנחה mincha. על ידיה וביד
הכהן מים המרים *Venosan mincha al yadeha uveyad hacohen mayim hamarim*. And
then after that, then you do the whole thing about the water.
ונתנה המנחה על ידיה וביד הכהן מי המרים mei ha-marim, and then
after that, then you do the whole thing about the waving of
the מנחה mincha and ומשביע ומתנה עמה, u-mashbia u-matneh imah, then you
make her to take an oath. וכותב את המגילה ומחה והשקה ve-khotev
et ha-megillah u-machah ve-hishkah and then he scrapes away the מגילה megillah
and he makes her drink it, okay, ומשקה ונוטל מנחתה מתוך כפיפה
מצרית ונותן לתוך כלי שרת u-mashke ve-notel minchatah mi-tokh kefifah mitzrit ve-noten
le-tokh kli sharet and then you take it and you put it
into a holy vessel and ומגיש קומץ ומקטיר u-magish kometz u-maktir and
then you offer it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And so that's a
very nice distillation of I don't know ten פסוקים psukim or more
in the תורה. Torah, Anyway, as we're going to go through we
can see that our order is not consistent with the order in
the תורה, Torah and already the most obvious one is we have
the disheveling of the woman before discussing the מנחה. mincha, Okay, so
now תוספות lands with a question, ולא ידענו למה שינה התנא הסדר.
ve-lo yadanu lamah shinah ha-tanna ha-seder. Number one, I don't know why
the תנא tanna is changing the order, maybe there's some literary reason,
some way of organizing the presentation, or, or ואם סדר התנא דוקא
סדר פרשה. ve-im seder ha-tanna davka seder parashah. And does when we
actually להלכה le-halakhah want to know how you go through the procedure,
should we assume you follow the order in the פרשה parashah, and
the reason it's different here is for literary reasons but ultimately the
order as described in the פרשה, parashah or maybe the תנא tanna
actually thinks that the פרשה is not in the sequential order and
he's presenting it as the sequential order, which is very hard to
imagine the גמרא Gemara would so radically redefine the order in the
תורה Torah. without telling you that it was doing. I'm not saying
it couldn't, but it would normally tell you that it was doing
it like it does by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in the עבודה.
Avodah. Right. But it tells you, the גמרא Gemara there tells you
that this it's not like the order it sounds like in the
תורה. Torah, Here all you just have is the presentation in the
משנה. mishnah. So it certainly feels that the order would follow the
order of the תורה, but it raises a question as why is
the information being organized differently in this משנה. mishnah. So that's something
to think about.
I think it will allude to that, to that סוגיא sugya in,
right.
Okay. תניא אבא חנין אומר משום רבי אליעזר: tanya Abba Chanin omer
mishum Rabbi Eliezer:
Why do you do this? כדי לייגע, kedei le-yage'a, to weary her.
You make her sort of you have her holding on. Now how
does keeping the the מנחה mincha? in her hands weary her? I
mean we'll take a look at what that exactly meant, we'll discuss,
but the purpose is to weary her כדי שתחזור בה, kedei she-tachzor
bah, in order that she should repent and admit her sin. אם
כך חסה תורה על עוברי רצונו קל וחומר על עושי רצונו. im
kakh chasah Torah al overei retzono kal va-chomer al osei retzono. And
look how much God cares for sinners, that he, God would rather
she admit her sin and not have to suffer the punishment of
the מי המרים, and if that's how much God cares for even
sinners, how much more does God care for those that do God's
will.
Well, what happens to her if she admits?
If she admits then she gets divorced, but there's no, that's it
and she doesn't get her כתובה. ketubah. Otherwise she's going to drink
the water and she'll explode and die according to the משנה. mishnah.
וממאי משום דחסה הוא? u-mimai mishum de-chasah hu? How do you know
that the reason we try to get her to admit is because
we want her, we're concerned for her life and her well-being? דילמא
כי היכי דלא תמחק מגילה? dilma ki heikhi de-lo timachak megillah? Maybe
we're doing it because as it becomes clear in other משניות, mishnayot,
we don't want God's name to be erased unnecessarily. Very different concern.
Is the concern her well-being or is the concern the erasing of
God's name? So the גמרא Gemara says no, קסבר משקה ואחר כך
מקריב את מנחתה. kasavar mashke ve-achar kakh makriv et minchatah. So this
תנא tanna who says the only issue is protecting her and not
God's name, understands that the מנחה mincha is actually brought after she
is made to drink. Now if you remember, that sounds a little
bizarre because we understand that as soon as she drinks it's like
duck, get back, she might explode! Right? If he brings the מנחה
mincha, after, what happened to the water? So רשי Rashi explains משקה
המים ואחריו רק מביא מנחתה mashke ha-mayim ve-acharav rak mevi minchatah and
ומיהו כל זמן שלא קרבה מנחתה אינה נבדקת. u-mihu kol zeman she-lo
karvah minchatah einah nivdeket. But the effects of the water are postponed
until the מנחה mincha is brought because obviously once you hit the
climax of the effects of the water it's like what are you
doing after? No no, you drink the water, you bring the מנחה
mincha, and then we'll see what's going to happen. But since she
already drank the water, there's no longer protecting God's name from being
erased. So if we want her to admit after drinking the water
before the מנחה mincha is brought, it's only in order to
we're careful for her well-being. דאם משום מגילה הא נמחקה לה. de-im
mishum megillah ha nimchakah lah. Because if the concern was God's name,
it's already been erased. Yeah.
So meaning that all that thing about trying to convince her not
to do it or I mean to admit happens after she drinks
the water?
No no no, we try to get her all along to admit.
But here but this תנא tanna is saying even after we certainly
there's the concern of erasing God's name and we try to get
her to admit beforehand and we dishevel her and all those things
to get her to admit beforehand. But this תנא tanna is saying
that even after the name has been erased, we try to get
her to admit in order for her well-being. Right. Because she already
drank the water.
After she's drunk the water. The water won't have the effect if
she admits and you don't bring the מנחה. mincha It'll only according
to this it'll only have the effect. Right. That's why we try
to get her admit now. Admit now even though you've drunk the
water so that and then we stop it right here and it
won't have the effect. Yeah.
Yeah. And then it's like like the last drop of whatever it
makes it. Exactly, exactly. It's like that thing. Exactly, the thing that
makes it explode is the bringing of the מנחה. mincha Okay, now
by the way, while this sounds bizarre that you're bringing the מנחה
Mincha after the water because I guess and I think in all
of our imagination the water was the last thing, you might remember
that תוספות just said that that's exactly what the פסוקים psukim, say.
When תוספות was going through the פסוקים, psukim he says, he says
וכתב מגילה ומחה והשקה ונוטל מנחתה ונותנה לתוך כלי ומניפה ומגישה ומקטירה.
vechatav megilla umacha vehishka venotel minchata venotna letoch kli umenifa umegisha umaktira.
That's exactly what the פסוקים pesukim say. She drinks the water and
then she brings the מנחה, Mincha but we read it here, it
sounds so bizarre, right? So it's actually quite interesting, right, in our
and the גמרא Gemara has to point out he holds this opinion,
right, taking as for granted that the normal assumption would be that
the drinking would be at the end. Okay, let's keep on going.
How is the, how is the name erased? What do they do?
They write it?
They write out the name and then they, they scrape. Yeah, yeah,
we'll get to that. כל המנחות. So now we're comparing it, all
the מנחות menachot are come with, come what do you call? Oh,
beginning and end כלי שרת, kli sharet. and this begins in a
non-כלי שרת. kli sharet, So the גמרא Gemara says רמינו, raminu, I'll
ask you, סדר מנחות כיצד, seder menachot keitzad, how do you bring
a מנחה? minchah. אדם מביא מנחה מתוך ביתו, adam meivi mincha mitoch
beito, you bring your מנחה minchah. from your house, you know, your,
your flour בקלתות של כסף ושל זהב, bekaltot shel kesef veshel zahav,
in various types of vessels of gold and silver, ונותנה לתוך כלי
שרת, venotna letoch kli sharet, then you put it in a holy
vessel, ומקדשה, umekadsha, and you sanctify it. The גמרא Gemara will discuss
it sounds like you have to do an act of sanctifying it
or an intention to sanctify it, בכלי שרת, ונותן עליה שמנה ולבונתה,
venoten aleha shamna ulevonata,
and you, still the owner, not even the כהן, kohen, put on
it the oil and the frankincense, ומוליכה כהן, umolicha kohen,
and then you bring it to the כהן, kohen, וכהן מוליכה אצל
מזבח, vekohen molicha etzel mizbeach, and the כהן kohen then brings it
to the altar, ומגישה בקרן דרומית מערבית, umegisha bekeren dromit maaravit,
and touches it on the southwest corner of the altar. We'll discuss
why in a minute. כנגד חודה של קרן, keneged chuda shel keren,
by the point of the, of the, you know, of the corner,
ודיו, vedayo,
and that's sufficient. We'll see why, why he had to say that,
that word. ומסלק את הלבונה לצד אחד, umesalek et halevona letzad echad,
moves the frankincense to one side, וקומץ ממקום שנתרבה שמנה, vekometz mimakom
shenitrabba shamna, and he takes a handbreadth from the place where there's
like the oil has been well mixed into it. And the reason
that he moves the frankincense to one side is that his handbreadth
has to be only the oil and the flour, can't have anything
else in it. ונותנו לתוך כלי שרת, venotno letoch kli sharet, and
he puts the קומץ kometz that he now scooped out with his
hands, he you know releases it and puts it in a second
vessel, holy vessel. כהן, kohen, כהן kohen because now that's he took
the קומץ. kometz. It's like you're the owner, you bring the animal,
right, and then you know the כהן kohen actually, you don't need
a כהן kohen to שחט, shacht, but anyway normally the כהן kohen
שוחט, shochet, gets the, gets, you know, takes, you know, the דם,
dam, etc. So here too you prepare the whole מנחה, minchah the
כהן kohen comes and he takes the קומץ kometz which is like
the שחיטה shchita of the animal. He puts it in the vessel
which by the way is like the catching of the blood of
the animal in the vessel. There's all these parallels. Okay, ומקדשו, umekadsho,
and he sanctifies it בכלי שרת. Again, it sounds like you have
to be an act of sanctifying it. ומלקט את לבונתה, umelaket et
levonata,
so that's the handbreadth, that's in that special, second vessel, and he
also collects all of the frankincense ונותנה עליו venotna alav and puts
it on top of the handbreadth. Okay, ומעלהו, umaalehu, and he brings
it to the top of the altar, ומקטירה, umaktira, and he offers
it up, which corresponds to the sprinkling of the blood or the
throwing of the blood on the altar, מכלי שרת, michli sharet, from
the holy vessel, ומולחו, umolcho, and he salts it. The גמרא Gemara
is going to say how could he salt it if he already
offered it up? So it says he brings it to the top
of the altar in order to offer it up, and he salts
it because everything gets salt, ונותנו על גבי אישים, venotno al gabei
ishim, and he puts it on the fire, on the fire. קרב
הקומץ, karav hakometz, once the handbreadth has been offered, שיריה נאכלין, shiureha
neechalin, the remainder of the מנחה minchah, can be eaten, ורשאין כהנים
ליתן לתוכה יין ושמן ודבש, urashain kohanim liten letocha yayin veshemen udvash,
and they can now do anything they want with the מנחה, mincha,
they can spice it up and they can put oil and honey
and, and wine, ואין אסורין, veein assurin, they're not limited to do
anything with the מנחה mincha, אלא מלחמץ, ela milachmetz,
they cannot let it become ferment.
Doesn't this was the, the
oil and flour that was not part of the...
Right. שיריה, shiureha, the remainder of the מנחה mincha, which has to
be eaten by the כהנים kohanim in the עזרה. azara. Okay, קתני
מיהא, katani miha, okay,
that was the whole very nice distilled description, but now look, it
says קתני מיהא, katani miha, it says nonetheless, where was I, I
lost my place, בקלתות של כסף בקלתות של זהב, bekaltot shel kesef
bekaltot shel zahav, that first you brought it in gold and silver
vessels and then you put it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
So you see that a מנחה mincha, begins in a non-כלי שרת.
kli sharet, So it's no difference than this. You know, you said
all מנחות Menachot start and end in a כלי שרת, kli sharet.
this starts in some mundane vessel. No, all מנחות also don't start
in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. אמר רב פפא אימא בכלים הראויים
לכלי שרת. amar Rav Papa eima bekeilim harauyim likli sharet. No, no,
no, all מנחות start in nice vessels, vessels that are fit to
be כלי שרת, kli sharet, gold and silver vessels. This starts in
some type of a, you know, of a, of a like a
hemp vessel, you know, which is unfit for being a כלי שרת.
Kli Shareit Okay, so now why is it unfit? So the גמרא
Gemara says מכלל דכפיפה מצרית
לא חזיא, michlal dechfiffa mitzrit lo chazya, so that sounds like this
type of a, you know, what is that thing that baskets are
made out of? Is that hemp? Wick? Wicker? Wicker. Okay. So okay,
so it sounds like that's, I think that's what it is, and
it sounds like wicker is not fit for being a כלי שרת.
Kli Shareit. כמאן, keman, who's that going like? דלא כרבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה. delo keRabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, כלי שרת שעשאן של עץ, klei sharet sheasaan shel etz,
if they're made out of wood and presumably wicker is seen like
a type of wood. רבי פוסל, Rebbi posel, Rebbi says it's invalid
for a כלי שרת, Kli Shareit, ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מכשיר. veRabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda machshir. So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו תימא רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה. Afilu teima Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda. No, it can
even go like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda. אימא
דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה בחשובים. Eima de-amar Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda
be-chashuvim. He would allow it to be in a כלי שרת Kli
Shareit if it was like a nice thing out of wood, carved
wood, very fancy and nice. בבזויים מי אמר? Be-vizuyim mi amar? Not
in some type of a lowly vessel. He would not allow a
lowly wood wicker vessel, that he would not allow. So לית ליה
לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Leis lei le-Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda? Do you
think he doesn't hold of הקריבהו נא לפחתך? Hakrivehu na le-pechatecha? Is
this something fit to bring before God? So it has to actually
be something that is fit. פחתך Pechatecha means like to an officer,
to a governor. If this is not something that you would bring
before a person of authority, then how much more so can you
not bring it before God. So what's interesting is that it's not
just like a value that's being stated, but it actually invalidates something
that doesn't meet that standard from being a כלי שרת. Kli Shareit?
So of course it really becomes halakhically prevents something from being a
כלי שרת, Kli Shareit which raises two questions. Question number one is
like Michael said before when the משנה Mishna said if she was
beautiful, you wouldn't do certain things, like who gets to decide if
she's beautiful? So who gets to decide whether this is a fit
or enough of a vessel or not? Is there a כהן Kohen
that gets to decide whether what constitutes a quality vessel? And also
let's say it was gold or silver but it also was like
mangled and in some way that even though it's of precious metal,
it's not appropriate to bring to as a way of honoring somebody,
would that also be invalid? Or is it the combination of the
two? Lowly material and not done in a nice way? Yeah, lowly
material on either around but we're talking about this two pages after
we had the study group in Shul with their money. Well, careful
with their money. Right, right, well that's a good point, careful with
their money not to waste it. But then there's the opposite idea
for the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash Right, the flip is that the
גמרא Gemara says by the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash like אין עניות
במקום עשירות. Ein aniyut be-makom ashirut. Like the whole idea of the
בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash, is a place of wealth and status and
therefore we don't use cheap things. So yeah, it's an interesting question
what you spend your money on. Okay, point taken. Yes. I just
pointed out that Jen just remembered what was two דפים Dapim ago.
Right, there you go. ונתנה לכלי. U-netana li-khli. Have a כלי שרת
Kli Shareit that's outside of the temple? Like in other words could
you bring something that is a כלי שרת? Kli Shareit Right. So
I'm sorry, you mean can you take a כלי שרת Kli Shareit.
outside of the outside of the temple? In other words if you're
bringing something you're saying what's the quality when they're originally bringing it
from their home? Right, no no right. It doesn't become a כלי
שרת Kli Shareit either. It's just saying that by normal מנחות you
would bring them in a vessel that in theory could be a
כלי שרת Kli Shareit. because that would be respectful of it. But
it wouldn't and then you would when you got to the temple
you would transfer it to a כלי שרת. Kli Shareit. It can
only be in the temple. Yes, you only ever כלי שרת Kli
Shareit in the temple, correct. Okay. ונתנה לכלי שרת. U-netana li-khli shareit.
So now you're in the temple and you put... now we're going
to look at this discussion of a normal מנחה mincha. before we
get back to the סוטה. Sotah. Okay, so you put it in
a כלי שרת. Kli Shareit וקדשה בכלי שרת Ve-kiddesha bi-khli shareit and
you sanctify it in the כלי שרת. Kli Shareit Sounds like that's
a separate act. So the גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה כלי שרת
אין מקדשין אלא מדעת. Shema mina kli shareit ein mekadeshin ela mi-da'at.
It sounds like that when you put something in a כלי שרת
Kli Shareit. to sanctify it, it requires intention to sanctify it. Just
the being in the כלי שרת Kli Shareit. doesn't sanctify it automatically.
And that's a question, that's actually a debate in the גמרא Gemara
whether maybe just the putting it even without intention automatically sanctifies. It's
like a weird job, why else would you put it in? Yeah,
but let's say you weren't thinking. I mean, okay, we can normally
say that that's true, but the question is do we assume that
as a fundamental principle it needs intention? And here it says like
you sanctified, it sounds like there was an intention. So the גמרא
Gemara's says no, אימא נותנה בכלי שרת לקדשה בכלי שרת. Eima notna
bi-khli shareit le-kadesha bi-khli shareit. You put it in to sanctify. Now
to sanctify also could reflect your intention. But the point is you
put, I think the גמרא's Gemara point is, you put it in
the כלי שרת Kli Shareit thereby sanctifying it in the כלי שרת.
kli sharet. It doesn't necessarily mean you had to intend it; the
result was it became sanctified. רש"י Rashi by the way points out
that you sanctify it before when you say המקדש? ha-mekadesh? No, "I
am מַקְדִּישׁ makdish my flour for a מנחה". mincha. Okay, but that
only is קדושת פה. Kedushat peh. And where it's not considered קדושת
הגוף, Kedushat ha-guf, an intrinsic קדושה Kedusha that defines its identity. And
the difference is is that whether you can redeem it, if you
took it out of the בית המקדש, does it invalidate it? All
of that intrinsic identity comes when it's put in the כלי שרת.
kli sharet? Okay, so now it continues... ונתן עליה שמן ולבונה. Ve-natan
aleha shemen u-levona. Then you, even the owner, now it's in the
כלי שרת kli sharet in the עזרה, Azarah, you put on it
the oil and the frankincense, שנאמר ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה,
she-ne'emar ve-yatzak aleha shemen ve-natan aleha levona, which if you look in
the פסוקים are talking still about the owner before it's brought before
the כהן Kohen gives it. ומוליכה אצל כהן, U-molicha etzel kohen, which
is the next פסוק, pasuk דכתיב והביאה אל בני אהרן. de-khtiv ve-hevi'ah
el bnei Aharon. For instance, it says you put on the oil
then it says and you bring it to the sons of Aaron.
הכהן מוליכה אצל מזבח, Ha-kohen molicha etzel mizbe'ach, and the כהן Kohen
brings it to the altar, דכתיב והגישה אל המזבח, de-khtiv ve-higisha el
ha-mizbe'ach, he shall bring it to the altar. מגישה בקרן דרומית מערבית
כנגד חודה של קרן ודיו. Magisha be-keren dromit ma'aravit ke-neged chudah shel
keren ve-dayo. You put it towards the southeast corner, southwest corner, and
that's sufficient. Now why the southwest corner and what does sufficient mean?
So מנלן, Menalan, where do you get this from? דכתיב... de-khtiv... You
put it towards the southeast corner, southwest corner, and that's sufficient. Now,
why the southwest corner, and what does sufficient mean? So מנלן, menalan,
where you get this from? דכתיב וזאת תורת המנחה, dichtiv vezot torat
haminchah,
this is the law of the מנחה. הקרב אותה בני אהרן לפני
ה׳ אל פני המזבח. hakrev otah bnei Aharon lifnei Hashem el pnei
hamizbeach. Bring it in front of God by the face of the
altar. וזאת תורת המנחה, Vezot torat haminchah, this is the law of
the מנחה. הקרב אותה בני אהרן לפני ה׳ אל פני המזבח. Hakrev
otah bnei Aharon lifnei Hashem el pnei hamizbeach. Bring it in front
of God by the face of the altar. דתניא, detanya, now you
have to understand is, I should have brought a diagram, but let's
try it like this. Let's say this is the עזרה Azarah here,
right? This whole thing here. And this is the היכל, Heichal, right?
This is the east, that's the west, that's the opening of the
היכל. Heichal. Okay, the מזבח mizbeach is here and the ramp to
the מזבח mizbeach is here, right? So פני ה׳ pnei Hashem means
on this side of the מזבח mizbeach facing, you know, facing the
היכל, Heichal, which is on the west. פני המזבח pnei hamizbeach means
the face of it where you go when you walk up the
ramp is this side, which is the south. So one thing says
פני המזבח, pnei hamizbeach, the south, the other says לפני ה׳, lifnei
Hashem, facing God, which is the west. So the only way we
do both is to put it at the southwest corner. Right?
So that's how you get.
So let's take a look.
It says, where are we? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraita, לפני
ה׳ יכול במערב, lifnei Hashem yachol bema'arav, maybe in the west? Because
that's what לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem would suggest, right? The side of
the altar that's facing the היכל. Heichal. תלמוד לומר אל
פני המזבח, talmud lomar el pnei hamizbeach, the face of the altar,
which is the south where the ramp comes up. אי אל פני
המזבח יכול בדרום? i el pnei hamizbeach yachol badarom? If it's the
face of the altar, maybe it should be in the south? תלמוד
לומר לפני ה׳. talmud lomar lifnei Hashem. No, it's got to be
before God. So one thing says west, one thing says south.
הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How you satisfy both of that? מגישה בקרן
דרומית מערבית כנגד חודו של קרן ודיו. magishah bekeren dromit ma'aravit keneged
chudo shel keren vidayo. You put it at the southwest corner, you
touch the actual point of the corner, ודיו, vidayo, and that's enough.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the touching is similar to the throwing
of the blood on the altar, by the way. Okay. By the
way, but
you know there is a difference because, well,
the מנחה has to actually be burnt on the altar, whereas by
the קרבן, the throwing of the blood sort of finish, I mean
obviously you burn the innards and so on, but the basic הקרבה
hakravah is satisfied once the blood is put on the altar, whereas
by the מנחה, right, the ultimately the הקרבה hakravah is the burning
of the קומץ kometz of the קומץ. kometz.
But this does parallel the throwing of the blood, at least in
terms of the act. Right? Exactly. To the horn. Exactly. So now,
so that's one דרשה. drasha. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has a different take on this. אמר יכול יגישנה
במערבה של קרן או בדרומה של קרן. amar yachol yagishenah bema'aravah shel
keren o bidromah shel keren.
Maybe you should go to the, I don't know, do you go
to the west? Do you go to the south? אמרת, amarta, which
one, which פסוק pasuk do I follow? Like he thinks it's an
either or. You got to make your choice of. אמרת כל מקום
שאתה מוצא שני מקראות. amarta kol makom she'ata motzeh shenei mikra'ot. You
have two verses that seem to contradict. אחד מקיים עצמו ומקיים דברי
חבירו. echad mekayem atzmo umekayem divrei chaveiro. One
you can go by its literal sense and actually it will deal
with it, it'll satisfy the demands of the other verse. ואחד מקיים
עצמו ומבטל דברי חבירו. ve'echad mekayem atzmo umevatel divrei chaveiro. And if
you focus on the other one in its literal sense,
you just would satisfy it but you wouldn't satisfy the other verse.
So which one do you think you're going to take? So you'll
take the one that works for both. מניחים את זה שמקיים עצמו
ומבטל את חברו. menichim et zeh shemekayem atzmo umevatel et chaveiro. You
leave aside the פסוק pasuk that to take it as the dominant
פסוק would not satisfy the other one.
ותופסים את שמקיים עצמו ומקיים חברו. vetofsim et shemekayem atzmo umekayem chaveiro.
The one that both, that can satisfy itself and that addresses the
other פסוק as well. Now how is that going to play out?
Which one are we going to choose? We have to choose one
that fits both. כשהוא אומר לפני ה׳ במערב, keshehu omer lifnei Hashem
bema'arav, if you were to focus on the לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem
in the west, ביטלת פני המזבח, bitalta pnei hamizbeach, there would be
no element of the face of the altar. Because if it's on
the west side, it's not at all on the south. There's no
element of the face of the altar. ביטלת פני המזבח בדרום. bitalta
pnei hamizbeach badarom. But here's how the other one will work for
both. וכשאתה אומר אל פני המזבח בדרום, vecheshe'ata omer el pnei hamizbeach
badarom, but if you do it on the south side, קיימת לפני
ה׳ במערב. kiyamta lifnei Hashem bema'arav.
So then you satisfy in front of God in the west. How?
Because let's say again, if this is the היכל
Heichal and this is the מזבח, mizbeach, imagine normally we assume that
the מזבח mizbeach is the size of the מזבח mizbeach 32 אמה
amah by 32 אמה amah is exactly opposite the היכל. Heichal. Okay,
so if you're on the south of, if you're on the south
of the מזבח, mizbeach, you're not in front of the היכל Heichal
at all. But what would be if, not what would be, he's
going to say that the whole מזבח mizbeach was here, right? So
that if you were at the face, the south face of the
מזבח, mizbeach, you would still be standing in front of the היכל.
Heichal. You understand? Right.
No.
No. He but he says if the מזבח mizbeach is here, if
you put it on the west side, you're not getting the face
of it at all. But if you put it on the face
of it, especially near the edge, it could be seen as still
directly opposite, right, because directly opposite the opening of the היכל.
Heichal. So that's how you are מקיים שניהם. mekayem sheneihem.
You know what I'm having trouble with? What? If you're standing in
front of the כותל, kotel, and you're just looking straight
ahead.
No, no, because this is the we call this the west side
of the altar. Right. Not the way you're facing. This is the
west side of the altar, the south side of the altar. If
you sprinkle it here, the blood is לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. Okay.
Got it. All right, not the blood, the מנחה, whatever it is.
Okay. So, okay. Okay, הגיעו זו לשם בפינת המקצע. higi'o zo lesham
bepinat hamiktzo'a. הכיצד? heikatzad? So what do you do? מגישה לדרומה של
קרן. magishah lidromah shel keren. You put it at the south לדרומה
של קרן, lidromah shel keren,
and then you're fine. והיכן קיימתי? veheichan kiyamti? So the גמרא Gemara
says, so I don't get it, how is the south of the
מזבח mizbe'ach in front of Hashem? אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
כסבר האי תנא, kasavar hai tana, this תנא tana is of the
opinion, כולו מזבח בצפון קאי. kulo mizbe'ach batzafon kai. The entire altar,
right, the אולם Ulam here is exactly midpoint of the עזרה, Azarah,
like it's situated exactly in the middle of the width of the
עזרה. Azarah. And here was normally where we assume the מזבח mizbe'ach
is. But if you say the entire מזבח mizbe'ach is in the
north, right, if this line aligns through the middle, right, is exact
midpoint, so if the entire מזבח mizbe'ach is in the north, the
end of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right, is exactly at the front of
the middle point of the אולם Ulam of
the היכל. Heichal. כולו מזבח בצפון קאי. kulo mizbe'ach batzafon kai.
מאי ודייו? mai vedayo? Now what does ודייו vedayo mean? Just put
it at the corner and you're done. Of course you're done. What
do you mean? אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, איצטריך, itzterich, you
need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka datach amina, תיבעי הגשה tiba'ei hagashah
מנחה גופה, mincha gufah, maybe you have to touch the actual physical
מנחה, not just touch the vessel. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan,
that's just touch the vessel. ואימא הכי נמי, ve'eima hachi nami, maybe
you should. It says you touch the מנחה, והגישה אל המזבח. vehigishah
el hamizbe'ach. אמר קרא, Amar kra, והקריבה הכהן והגישה אל המזבח. vehikrivah
hakohen vehigishah el hamizbe'ach. מה הקרבה אצל הכהן בכלי, mah hakravah etzel
hakohen bichli, אף הגשה אל המזבח בכלי. af hagashah el hamizbe'ach bichli.
The same way when it says you bring it, it means in
a vessel, so when you touch it, it means in a vessel.
Let's just do one more line. ומסלק את הלבונה לצד אחד. umesalek
et halevonah letzad echad. You move the frankincense to one side, כי
היכי דלא תקמוץ בהדי מנחה, ki heichi dela tikmotz behadi mincha, so
when you take the קומץ, kometz, you shouldn't have a little bit
of the לבונה levonah, mixed in with the מנחה, with the flour
and the oil. כדתנן, kidtnan, קמץ ועלה בידו צרור או גרגיר מלח
או קורט של לבונה. kamatz ve'alah beyado tzeror o gargar melach o
koret shel levonah. If when you took the קומץ, kometz, you had
a little rock or a little a little like a little, you
know, whatever it is, crystal, grain of salt, right, or a little
grain of the frankincense, it's פסול pasul because it's not your entire
קומץ kometz is not out of מנחה. וקומץ ממקום שנתרבה שמנה. vekometz
mimakom shenitravah shemanah.
And you take the קומץ kometz in the place where the oil,
if there's a lot of oil, what's well mixed. מנלן? menalan? דכתיב,
dechtiv, מסלתה ומשמנה. misaltah umishmanah. Okay. מגירשה ומשמנה. megirshah umishmanah. Yeah, I
got גירש geresh right. Okay, so it emphasizes its oil, means there
has to be like a lot of oil there. Okay. ונותנו לתוך
כלי שרת ומקדשו בכלי שרת. venotno letoch kli sharet umekadsho bichli sharet.
Again, it sounds like you do an act of sanctifying, it doesn't
happen automatically, right? למה לי דאקדישיה חד זימנא? lamah li de'akdisheih chad
zimna? Oh no, it asks another question. You already sanctified it in
the כלי שרת. kli sharet Why are you sanctifying the קומץ kometz
in another כלי שרת? kli sharet, This is just the קומץ kometz
now. Why are you sanctifying that? So the גמרא says, מידי דהוה
אדם. midi dehavah adam. Not אדם. adam. אדם. adam. Just like it
happens by blood. דם אף על גב דקדישיה סכין בצואר בהמה. dam
af al gav dekdisheih sakin betzavar behemah. When you שחט shacht the
בהמה, this is an interesting parallel. The סכין sakin is the knife
is a כלי שרת kli sharet and the knife sanctifies the blood.
The same way
the
כלי שרת sanctifies the מנחה. But even though the knife sanctifies the
blood, the blood is caught in a כלי שרת, which shows another
act of sanctification. So even though the knife sanctified it, הדר מקדשי
ליה בכלי שרת, hadar mikadshei leih bichli sharet, nevertheless you catch the
blood in a כלי שרת which sanctifies it a second time to
make it fit for being thrown on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. It's one
thing to sanctify it, it's another thing to get it to the
level to being put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. הכא נמי לא שנא.
hacha nami lo shana. Here too, by the לבונה,
it is no different. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.
ישר כח, yasher koach,
Rabbi.